Guide to the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers 1647-1917 (bulk 1840-1917) MS 605
New-York Historical Society
- Series I Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
  - Subseries 3: Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Legal papers 1856, 1866, 1869
    One contract (in French), which appears to concern the purchase of a piece of art; a release by Rutherfurd Stuyvesant to the New York Life Insurance Co.; a contract to lay a cranberry bog on a farm (presumably Tranquillity).
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Legal Papers, 1856, 1866, 1869 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 4: Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Court Papers 1876, 1900
    Rutherfurd Stuyvesant vs. Richard O'Brien; suit over land in NYC. The items appear to be a State of Case and a summons.
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Court Papers, 1876, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant: Other Subseries
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- List of Tenants in NYC, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant --Certificates, etc., 1897, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Invitation to Prince of Wales' Ball, 1860 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Armor Collection -- "Papers of the Dino Collection", 1903 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Armor Collection -- Diagram of Medieval Lance (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Clippings re Yachts, [1903] (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Steam Yacht "Arcturus" -- Specifications, [1895] (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Steam Yacht "Arcturus" -- Plans, [1895] (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- permit to Sport [Hunt] at Alexandretta, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Description of Paintings for Sale, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Coat of Arms, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- membership Badge, National Horse Show Association, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Photographs, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Blank Notebook, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Diaries, 1869 - 1892 (Box 9, Folder unknown container)
- Series II: Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant
  Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant (18??-1879) was the first Mrs. Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. Most of the material in the series is correspondence, which detail her close relationship with her sisters-in-law, Margaret and Louisa M. Rutherfurd.
  - Subseries 1: Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant - Letters received N.D., 1867-1879
    Many of these letters are undated, and many are addressed to "Mamie". Most of the content of the letters concerns family and social affairs. Frequent correspondents are Louisa Morris Rutherfurd (1859-1892) ("Loulou"), Margaret Rutherfurd White ("Daisy"), Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd, Ellen Pierrepont, and Henry Pierrepont.
    - Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1867 - 1879 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 2: Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant - Letters Sent to Her Family N.D., 1872-1873
    Some of the letters are addressed "Dear Sisters." The letters are addressed from New York, and are presumably to the family of Lewis Morris Rutherfurd.
    - Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant -- Letters Sent to Her Family, N.D. 1872 - 1873 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 3: Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1865, 1867, 1885
    Most of the material in this subseries (one folder) is from a European tour taken by Rutherfurd Stuyvesant and Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant in 1867. Most of the material is in French.
    - Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1865, 1867, 1885 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Series III: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant
  Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant (1727-1805) was a New York merchant and the father of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant (1778-1847) and Nicholas William Stuyvesant (1769-1833).
  - Subseries 1: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1781-1787
    Principal correspondents include Nicholas William Stuyvesant, Miles Cooper, Henry White, and John Leech. Much of the material has to do with Nicholas William Stuyvesant's stay in Scotland to pursue his education. In addition to news of Nicholas' progress and activities, Miles Cooper writes about events and attitudes in Great Britain during the closing years of the Revolution. Two bound volumes record accounts of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant's estate.
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1781 - 1787 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1775-1825
    Includes material pertaining to household items, house repairs (some perhaps on rental properties), and taxes. Material relating to business ventures itemizes costs of commodities like rum, pepper, and tea.
    Material after 1801 deals with the Estate of Peter Stuyvesant.
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1775 - 1784 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1785 - 1801 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1804 - 1825 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Reciepts -- Account Book, 1795 - 1805 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Volume -- Account Book -- Estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant, 1805 - 1824 (Volume Unknown container 666 for instance of Volume -- Account Book -- Estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant)
    - Volume -- Ledger -- Estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant, 1805 - 1812 (Volume Unknown container 667 for instance of Volume -- Ledger -- Estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant)
  - Subseries 3: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant - Legal Papers N.D., 1784-1804
    Material consists of deeds, contracts, award of arbitrators.
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant --Legal Papers, 1784 - 1799 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, N.D., 1785 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, 1800 - 1804 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 4: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant - Court Papers 1795, 1805
    Material from two suits: Two receipts from the case of Stephen Sayre vs. Peter Stuyvesant and Daniel Ludlow (1795) and a bill of costs from the case of Daniel Ludlow vs. Peter Stuyvesant (1805).
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Court Papers, 1795 - 1805 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant: Other Subseries
    - Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant -- Inventory of Effects, [1801] (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Peter Gerard Stuyvesant
  Peter Gerard Stuyvesant, the husband of Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant, was a New York businessman with extensive property holdings. It was under a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will that his grandnephew, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd, changed his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. Most of the material in this series reflects Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's interest in missions, charities, and education.
  - Subseries 1: Peter Gerard Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1794, 1804-1842
    Correspondents include Peter Augustus Jay, John Rutherfurd, and James Ewing. One letter of Peter Augustus Jay, from London in 1794, refers to the war in Europe, and makes a passing reference to the "insurgents" in the United States, presumably the Whiskey Rebellion insurgents. Many of the letters are from missionaries or clergymen, thanking Peter Gerard Stuyvesant for his support or patronage. These include John Westlake, B.B. Smith, and Joseph Wolff.
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1794 - 184? (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1840 - 1842 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Peter Gerard Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1800-1849
    Most of the material in this subseries consists of items concerning business matters, especially Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's property holdings in New York City, and his charitable giving.
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1800 - 1849 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Peter Gerard Stuyvesant - Legal Papers 1784-1805
    This subseries consists of bonds of various persons to Peter Gerard Stuyvesant, and leases. Most of this material relates to Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's properties in Manhattan. The Stuyvesant Institute is also a party to some on the agreements.
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Legal Papers, 1784 - 1845 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, 1806 - 1808 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, 1810 - 1822 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant: Other Subseries
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Diplomas, Certificates, Licenses, 1794 - 1802, 1833 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Diagram and Design of Estate (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Deduction of Title to Bowery, [1805] (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Peter Gerard Stuyvesant -- Farm Books, 1816 - 1821 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Series V: Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
  Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant was the wife of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant and seems to have been especially close to the family of her nephew, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd. Material in this series reflects her interest in church and missionary affairs, and contains some observations by her correspondents on political events.
  - Subseries 1: Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1801, 1828-1850, 1865-1873
    Correspondents include members of the Rutherfurd family, Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's husband, Peter Gerard Stuyvesant, and Archibald Russell. Subjects include, in addition to family matters, social events, an 1849 scandal in the Episcopal Church, Catholicism in the U.S., and European perceptions of Americans. Most of the material from the late 1860's is from Rutherfurd Stuyvesant, describing a European tour.
    - Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1801, 1828 - 1848 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1849 - 1850, 1865, 1867 - 1873 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1855
    One receipt, for fruit.
    - Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1855 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Matilde Stuyvesant
  Matilde Stuyvesant (18??-1948) was the second wife of Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. Most of the series consists of letters from her sons, Lewis and Alain. The series also contains a folder entitled [Matilde Stuyvesant] - Letters Received. Matilde Stuyvesant was the most likely recipient of the letters this folder.
  - Subseries 1 Matilde Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1902, 1917
    Most of the letters in this subseries are from Matilde Stuyvesant's two sons, Alain and Lewis R. ("Stuyve"). The letters concern the boys' studies and activities at school. Herbert H. Hawkins, who appears to have been the headmaster of one school the boys attended, Ecole de L'Ile de France, occasionally writes regarding the boys' academic progress. A form letter from the Ecole de L'Ile de France, dated September 1914, informs parents that the area of Liancourt, where the school was located, has been occupied by the Germans.
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1902 - 1914 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1915 - 1917 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2 Matilde Stuyvesant - Postcards Received 1910-1912
    Postcards from her sons, while the boys were on vacation.
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Postcards Received, 1910 - 1912 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: [Matilde Stuyvesant] - Letters Received N.D., 1903
    Letters, some in French, addressed to "Madame" or to "Elisabeth." These letters are probably to Matilde Stuyvesant. Mrs. Stuyvesant's middle name was Elisabeth, and no other person of that name appears in the collection contemporary with these letters.
    - [Matilde Stuyvesant] -- Letters Received, N.D., 1903 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 4: Matilde Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1903, 1905, 1907
    For clothes and household items, including two from Tiffany's.
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1903, 1905, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 5: [Matilde Stuyvesant] - Bill 1931
    Probably to Matilde Stuyvesant, who was the only "Mrs. Stuyvesant" in 1931.
    - [Matilde Stuyvesant] -- Bill, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 6: Matilde Stuyvesant - Newspaper Clippings 1904
    Subseries consists of clippings about Mrs. Stuyvesant's appearances at the opera, theater, etc.
    - Matilde Stuyvesant -- Newspaper Clippings, 1904 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Series VII: Nicholas William Stuyvesant (1722-1780)
  Nicholas William Stuyvesant (1722-1780) was a New York Merchant and the brother of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant. Most of the material in the series pertains to his business activities.
  - Subseries 1: Nicholas William Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1762, 1767
    Three letters, all from William Samuel Johnson of London. The letters deal with business affairs, with some personal content. In his letter dated July 10, 1767, Johnson discusses British reaction to American protests over the Stamp Act.
    - Nicholas William Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1762, 1767 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Nicholas William Stuyvesant (and Estate of -) - Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1747-1800
    Most of the material deals with the Estate of Nicholas William Stuyvesant. A receipt book, dated 1752-1753, includes entries for goods purchased, rents collected, and money collected apparently on behalf of other persons.
    - Nicholas William Stuyvesant (and Estate of -) -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1747 - 1800 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Nicholas William Stuyvesant (and Estate of -) -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts -- Receipt Book, 1752 - 1753 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3: Nicholas William Stuyvesant (and Estate of -) - Legal Papers 1758-1796
    Bonds, leases, conveyances, including a conveyance of a slave named Francisco from Henry Law to Nicholas William Stuyvesant in 1758.
    - Nicholas William Stuyvesant (and Estate of -) --Legal Papers, 1758 - 1796 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Nicholas William Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, 1762, 1773 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Series VIII: Alain Stuyvesant
  Alain Stuyvesant (1906-1954) was the son of Rutherfurd Stuyvesant and Matilde Stuyvesant. As well as the material detailed below, the series includes some of Alain Stuyvesant's school report cards and letters to Santa Claus.
  - Subseries 1: Alain Stuyvesant - Letters Received 1926
    One letter, from F.C. Mead. Mead briefly recounts his travels in India and Burma.
    - Alain Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Alain Stuyvesant: Other Subseries
    - Alain Stuyvesant -- Letters to Santa Claus, N.D. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Alain Stuyvesant -- Musical Notes, N.D. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Alain Stuyvesant -- Report Cards, 1913 - 1916 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Series IX: Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
  Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1903-1944) was the son of Rutherfurd Stuyvesant and Matilde Stuyvesant. As well as the material detailed below, the series includes some of Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's school report cards and letters to Santa Claus.
  - Subseries 1: Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1925,1926
    Most of the letters are from well-wishers congratulating Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant on his marriage, in 1925, to Rosalie Pillot. One letter, from [Sampuram Singh], describes a hunting incident involving a person identified as H.H.
    - Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D., 1925, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant: Other Subseries
    - Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters to Santa Claus, 1910, 1911 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Diary -- "Impressions of a Trip", 1915 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Report Cards, 1912 - 1917 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Series X: Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant
  Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant was the first wife of Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. They were married in 1925 and divorced in 1930.
  - Subseries 1: Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant - Letters Received 1925-1926
    Letter from well-wishers on her wedding, letters from her father, P. Stuyvesant Pillot, convey news about her family and New York society.
    - Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1925 - 1926 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Series XI: Mr. and Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
  - Mr. and Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant: Subseries
    - Mr. & Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - - Clippings, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Mr. & Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - - Postcards Received, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Mr. & Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - - Invitations, 1925, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Mrs. L. R. Stuyvesant -- Card Received, N.D. (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Series XII: Gerardus Stuyvesant
  Gerardus Stuyvesant (1691-1777) was the father of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant (1727-1805) and Nicholas William Stuyvesant (1722-1780).
  - Subseries 1: Gerardus Stuyvesant - Letters Received 1776
    One letter, August 21, 1776, from John Morin Scott. Scott answers Gerardus Stuyvesant's complaint that he has been driven from his house by the army, and has been forced to sleep in a barn.
    - Gerardus Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1796 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 2: Gerardus Stuyvesant - Legal Papers N.D., 1715, 1764-1776
    Primarily leases for properties in Albany County and New York City.
    - Gerardus Stuyvesant -- Legal Papers, N.D., 1715, 1770 - 1776 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Gerardus Stuyvesant -- Oversize Legal Papers, 1764, 1776 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 3: Gerardus Stuyvesant (Estate of -) - Receipt 1776
    To Abraham van Vlect for "sundry medicins" (sic).
    - Gerardus Stuyvesant (Estate of ) -- Receipt, 1776 (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Series XIII: Stuyvesant Family
  Includes correspondence addressed to unidentified family members, and accounts, bills, and receipts that cannot be attributed to a particular family member.
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Mr. [ ] Stuyvesant - - Letter Received, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Mr. [ ] Stuyvesant - - Receipt, 1784 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Mrs. [ ] Stuyvesant -- Letter Received, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Mrs. [ ] Stuyvesant -- Receipt, N.D. (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Mr. & Mrs. [ ] Stuyvesant -- Invitation Received, N.D. (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts -- Europe, N.D., 1865 - 1867 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Stuyvesant Family -- Clippings re Real Estate, N.D., 1918, 1930, 1954, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Series XIV: Stuyvesant Institute
  The Stuyvesant Institute was a library, museum, and lecture hall in New York City. The institute was built on land donated by Peter Gerard Stuyvesant.
  - Subseries 1: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" - Act of Incorporation 1836
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Act of Incorporation, 1836 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 2: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" - Correspondence 1839, 1840, 1842
    Includes Hamilton Fish writing to Peter Gerard Stuyvesant regarding the lawsuit of Theodosius G. Fowler et al. vs. Isaac Green Pearson et al.
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Correspondence, 1839, 1840, 1842 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 3: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1837-1842
    Most of the material concerns interest on bonds. An account book kept by Peter Gerard Stuyvesant from 1840 to 1842 records amounts received and paid to various persons.
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1837 - 1842 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Account book of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant, 1840 - 1842 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Subseries 4: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" - Legal Papers N.D., 1837-1842
    Mostly bonds and deeds. An 1835 deed from Issac Green Pearson and others includes a survey map of the area of New York City where the Stuyvesant Institute was located.
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Legal Papers, 1835 - 1839 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Subseries 5: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" - Court Papers [1834]
    Assorted papers concerning the case of Theodosius G. Fowler et al. vs. Isaac Green Pearson et al. There are no motions or pleas, or material pertaining to the arguments in or character of the case.
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- Court Papers, [1834] (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Subseries 6: "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -Deduction of Title of Mr. John McComb to Four Lots on Broadway [1832]
    Document tracing the ownership of land on which the Stuyvesant Institute stood, or in the vicinity of the Stuyvesant Institute.
    - "Stuyvesant Institute Papers" -- "Deduction of Title of Mr. John McComb to Four Lots on Broadway", [1832] (Box 14, Folder 31)
- Series XV: Lewis Morris Rutherfurd
  Lewis Morris Rutherfurd (1816-1892) was the son of Robert Walter Rutherfurd (1788-1871) and Sabina Morris Rutherfurd (1789-1857). He was an astrophysicist at Columbia University in New York City. Most of the material in the series consists of letters from his family; very little relates to his work as an astrophysicist. The series includes some articles written by him in his professional capacity.
  - Subseries 1: Lewis Morris Rutherfurd - Letters Received N.D., 1829, 1854-1892
    Most of the letters are from members of Lewis Morris Rutherfurd's immediate family, many from Lewis Morris Rutherfurd's son, Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. Subjects addressed by Rutherfurd Stuyvesant include his interest in yachting, his travels to Europe, his hunting trips to the western territories of the U.S. in the mid-1880's, his business interests (in which his father may have been involved), and occasionally politics.
    Persons who corresponded with Lewis Morris Rutherfurd regarding his work as an astronomer include G.B. Airy of the Royal Observatory in 1875, W.R. Pickering of Harvard in 1888, and J.K. Rees of Columbia University in 1890.
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, N.D. (1 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, N.D. (2 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, 1829, 1854 - 1879 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, 188?, 1880 - 1889 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, Jan. 1890 - May 1890 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, June 1890 - Dec. 1890 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, Jan. 1891 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, Feb. 1891 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, March 1891 - Dec. 1891 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Letters Received, Jan. 1892 - May 1892 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: Lewis Morris Rutherfurd - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1865-1892
    Primarily for household items, groceries, clothing, etc. Includes freight receipts from the Hudson & Lehigh RR for freight shipped to and from the family's New Jersey estate, Tranquillity.
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1865, 1867, 1880 - 1886 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1887 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1888, 1890 - 1892 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 3: Lewis Morris Rutherfurd - Legal Papers 1877
    Letters Testamentary naming Lewis Morris Rutherfurd executor of John W. Chanler.
    - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd -- Legal Papers, 1877 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Lewis Morris Rutherfurd: Other Subseries